Ignacio Mariano Sticco, PhD

Data Scientist

ignaciosticco@gmail.com

+54 (9) 11-6045-0304

linkedin.com/in/ignacio-sticco-0b606683/

ignaciosticco.github.io/

github.com/ignaciosticco

scholar.google.com/citations?user=Rb_GO6oAAAAJ&hl

Summary

Data scientist and PhD in Physics with extensive experience in data exploration and application of predictive models in real-world conditions. Enjoy solving complex problems, while offering simple solutions. Passionate about data analysis and enjoy teamwork. Focus on objectives so that results have the greatest possible business impact.

Experience

Data Scientist & Product Manager

Aeroterra • 2023-2024

- Led a team composed of 5 data scientists and software developers.
- Contributed to the design, ETLs and deployment of algorithms capable of detecting more than 1000 anomalies per day for the Argentinian Ministry of Security.
- Applied Machine Learning models to make predictions in the drinking water distribution industry.
- Conducted visualizations of georeferenced maritime traffic data comprising approximately 2.5 billion data points, empowering the Argentine Coast Guard to make informed decisions.

Doctoral Fellow

CONICET • 2018-2023

- Published 8 papers in international scientific journals, with a total of more than 150 citations.
- Programmed numerical simulations to improve panicked evacuations, resulting in a 70% reduction in evacuation time.
- Applied an evolutionary algorithm to optimize parameters within a pedestrian movement model, resulting in a 25% enhancement in model performance compared to prevailing state-ofthe-art models.
- Participated in more than 15 scientific conferences, giving talks, and presenting posters.
- Finished my Doctoral Thesis with the highest grade.

More information at: Google Scholar Profile

Data Scientist & Data Analyst

Futbol Sites Network • 2018

- Processed, visualized, and analyzed data to improve the performance of the company's web pages.
- Discovered a pattern capable of increasing the Average Time on Site by a factor of 3.
- Created dashboards with KPIs to monitor traffic on more than 30 web pages.

University Professor

Universidad de Buenos Aires & Universidad Argentina de la Empresa • 2017-2024

- Led courses with an enrollment of more than 50 students from all university levels (from first to last year).
- Gave theoretical, practical and laboratory classes both in person and virtually.

Skills

- Programming: Python (Pandas, NumPy, Matplotlib, Scipy, Sci-kit Learn, among others), SQL, MATLAB, NoSQL (MongoDB).
- **Tools**: Git, Linux, Latex, Jupyter Notebook.
- Visualization: Power Bl.
- Management: Team leadership, Agile methodologies, communication, storytelling.
- Languages: Spanish (native), English (B2).
- **Knowledge**: Statistics, physics, mathematics, research.

Education

PhD in Physics

Faculty of Exact and Natural Sciences, University of Buenos Aires 2018-2023

Licenciatura Physics (equivalent to Bachelor + Msc)

Faculty of Exact and Natural Sciences, University of Buenos Aires 2010-2016

Projects

- Programmed an identifier and tracker for pedestrians immersed in a crowd.
- Utilized Natural Language Processing (NLP) to analyze the sentiment of Google Maps reviews.
- Analyzed the centrality of the bus network in the City of Buenos Aires.
- Programmed a neural network from scratch to recognize handwritten digits.

More information at: Personal website

Courses & Certifications

- Workshop on Collaborative Scientific Software Development ICTP Trieste.
- Machine Learning Stanford (Coursera).
- Learning how to learn UC San Diego (Coursera).
- First Certificate in English (B2) Cambridge.

Interests & Tastes

- **Academics**: Science, technology, artificial intelligence, finance, economy, and politics.
- Sports: Swimming, jogging and calisthenics.
- **Domestic**: chatting (in person), drinking coffee, walking, going to the beach, reading, cooking.